When did you come here?
언제 여기에 왔나요?
half an hour ago
30분 전
But compared to this…
그런데 이것에 비하면…
Shouldn't you be asking me why I'm here?
내가 왜 여기 있는지 물어보면 안 되나요?
You already knew that
당신은 이미 그것을 알고 있었죠
from that day on
그날부터
How could I become you
내가 어떻게 네가 될 수 있겠어?
What the hell is going on
도대체 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는 걸까
I have to go back to the palace first
먼저 궁전으로 돌아가야 해
That's...
그건...
White mask
흰색 마스크
Black clothes
검은 옷
medical clothes
의료복
Eunjo, who was also present at the time, should have seen it more clearly than me.
그 자리에 함께 있던 은조는 나보다 더 똑똑히 봤어야 했다.
Is Dr. Hong also present?
홍 박사님도 계시나요?
How did you know I worked in the Robbery Bureau?
내가 강도국에서 일한다는 걸 어떻게 알았나요?
That…
그…
Anyway, luckily it was you who took the initiative to resolve this matter.
어쨌든, 다행히도 이 문제를 해결하기 위해 주도적으로 나선 것은 당신이었습니다.
It turned out to be you
당신인 것으로 드러났어요
Ji Tong
지통
Where is the lucky boy?
행운의 소년은 어디에 있나요?
Not here
여기가 아니야
Go look for it over there
가서 저기 좀 찾아봐
Will it go this way?
이대로 갈까요?
You are also a real person
당신도 실존인물이군요
If it was Ji Tong, he would have escaped without a trace long ago.
지통이었다면 오래전에 흔적도 없이 도망쳤을 것이다.
That's good
그거 좋다
Isn't this Eunjo?
이 사람은 은조 아닌가요?
what
무엇
That…
그…
Please help me...
도와주세요...
Eunjo Eunjo
은조 은조
What should I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
OMG
세상에
Why didn't you ask me in the first place?
왜 처음부터 나한테 물어보지 않았어?
Because I want to hide it for you
숨기고 싶으니까
that night
그날 밤
I heard the patrol talking about the reasons for hunting Ji Dong
순찰대가 지동을 사냥하는 이유에 대해 이야기하는 것을 들었습니다
Although Ji Tong’s name appears on the blood book,
혈액서에는 지통의 이름이 나와 있지만,
But you were having a wedding at that time
그런데 그 때 넌 결혼식 중이었어
It is impossible to kill Da Sijian
Da Sijian을 죽이는 것은 불가능합니다
Even if that's true
그게 사실이라고 해도
I will also choose to hide it
나도 숨기는 걸 선택하겠어
See you appear here
여기 나타나서 봐
Sure enough, he was wronged
물론, 그는 부당한 대우를 받았습니다
We should come here for the same reason, right?
우리도 같은 이유로 여기에 와야 하는 거겠죠?
Everyone thought that someone would come to clean up the fake Jitong's body.
모두 누군가가 가짜 지통의 시신을 치우러 올 것이라고 생각했습니다.
I'm sorry for hiding from you during this time
그동안 숨어서 미안해요
You don't need to apologize
사과할 필요는 없어
You stepped forward as a woman to help those people
그런 사람들을 돕기 위해 당신은 여자로서 나섰습니다.
It should have received applause
박수를 받았어야 했는데
So don't put that look on my face
그러니 내 얼굴에 그런 표정 짓지 마세요
Buried right there
바로 거기에 묻혀있어
Just let me give these sacrificial meals to Ji Tong
이 희생적인 식사를 Ji Tong에게 주도록 해주세요.
Who is over there
거기 누구야?
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
Could it be a wild beast in the mountains?
산속에 사는 야생동물이 아닐까?
Auntie proprietor, don’t worry
주인 아주머니, 걱정하지 마세요
I think you are the beast
내 생각엔 네가 짐승인 것 같아
What kind of trick are you trying to play?
어떤 종류의 속임수를 쓰려고 하시나요?
Do you know why he stopped?
그가 왜 멈췄는지 아세요?
That road is where tigers and other wild animals will appear.
그 길은 호랑이와 다른 야생 동물들이 나타날 곳입니다.
That's the person who caused you to be wronged
그 사람이 당신을 억울하게 만든 사람이에요
I must know who he is
나는 그 사람이 누구인지 알아야 해요
It's too dangerous. Let's catch up here today.
너무 위험해요. 오늘은 여기까지 따라잡자.
i don't care
난 상관없어
i care
난 상관해요
I don't want you to get hurt because of this.
이 일로 인해 당신이 상처받는 것을 원하지 않습니다.
You seem to have forgotten that your body is mine
네 몸이 내 것이라는 걸 잊어버린 것 같아
Go now and if you encounter a wild beast
지금 가서 만일 맹수를 만나거든
I was the one whose limbs were dismembered
나는 팔다리가 절단된 사람이었다
Yeah, I forgot about it for a moment
응, 잠시 잊어버렸어
Do you have anyone you doubt?
의심되는 사람이 있나요?
The murderer of Da Sijian
Da Sijian의 살인자
Someone who has a grudge against that adult
그 어른에게 원한을 품고 있는 사람
It probably occupies half of the entire capital city.
아마도 전체 수도의 절반을 차지할 것입니다.
In other words, people who want Da Si to remonstrate to death
즉, 다시가 죽음에 이르는 항의를 하길 원하는 사람들은
It takes up half of the capital.
자본금의 절반을 차지합니다.
I'm afraid it won't be easy to find the murderer now.
지금은 범인을 찾기가 쉽지 않을 것 같아요.
After tonight, he won't show his true colors again.
오늘 밤이 지나면 그는 다시는 본색을 보여주지 않을 것이다.
Why did he pretend to be a lucky boy and show up at the Robbery Hall?
그는 왜 운 좋은 소년인 척하며 강도당에 나타났는가?
Probably trying to take advantage of the death of the suspect Ji Dong
아마도 용의자 지동의 죽음을 이용하려던 것 같습니다.
Let this case come to an end
이 사건이 종결되게 해주세요
So he needs a suspect who can convince the people
그래서 그는 사람들을 설득할 수 있는 용의자가 필요합니다
And that person is Ji Dong, right?
그리고 그 사람이 바로 지동이죠?
People will think Ji Dong is really dead
사람들은 지동이 진짜 죽었다고 생각할 거야
He's just a thief
그 사람은 그냥 도둑이에요
Now he has a name and the rumors are out of control
이제 그는 이름이 생겼고 소문은 걷잡을 수 없게 되었습니다.
Although I feel sorry for the person who died,
돌아가신 분에게 안타까움을 느끼면서도
But it’s right that the name Gildong should disappear like this
하지만 길동이라는 이름은 이대로 사라져야 하는 게 맞다.
Wait
잠깐
What do you mean now
지금 무슨 말이야?
Will you continue to be a thief in the future?
앞으로도 계속 도둑질을 할 건가요?
This is the default
이것이 기본값입니다
I just can't answer that you won't do it anymore
더 이상 안 하겠다고 대답할 수가 없어요
I knew you were a lucky boy, but I still hid it for you
난 네가 운이 좋은 소년이라는 걸 알았지만 그래도 널 위해 숨겼어
Because at least during the body swapping period
적어도 신체 교환 기간 동안에는
You can't steal again
다시는 훔칠 수 없어
Of course, don't worry
물론이죠. 걱정하지 마세요.
Do you think I'm worried about myself?
내가 나 자신에 대해 걱정하고 있다고 생각합니까?
I said that as a woman, I would stand up and help those people.
나는 여자로서 일어나서 그 사람들을 돕겠다고 말했습니다.
It should have received applause
박수를 받았어야 했는데
But that's in the past, I can think of it this way
하지만 그건 옛날 일이니까 이렇게 생각할 수도 있겠네요
But it's different now
하지만 지금은 달라
That woman is you
That woman is you
Burglary, fall and homicide charges
절도, 추락, 살인 혐의
All threats fall on you
모든 위협은 당신에게 달려 있습니다
You know when I went to identify the body of the fake Ji Tong
내가 가짜 지통의 시신을 확인하러 갔을 때를 알지?
How do I feel inside?
내 마음은 어떤가요?
Could it be because I hid it for you?
내가 당신을 위해 숨겨두었기 때문일까요?
It's because I failed to stop you that things became like this
널 막지 못해서 상황이 이렇게 된 거야
I have complained and hated myself
나는 나 자신을 불평하고 미워했습니다
Nothing like that
그런 건 없어
I've never been caught before...
한번도 잡히지 않았는데...
Haven't you been caught by me?
나한테 잡힌 적 없어?
I warn you
나는 당신에게 경고합니다
Whether it's your body or my body
너의 몸이든 내 몸이든
As long as you dare to come out and steal things again
감히 나와서 물건을 다시 훔치기만 하면
Will definitely be caught
반드시 잡힐 것이다
It will still fall into my hands when the time comes
때가 되면 여전히 내 손에 떨어지겠지
I didn’t expect to be seen through again
다시 볼 수 있을 거라고는 기대하지 않았어
I'm going back first
나 먼저 돌아갈게
stop
중지
Why is that girl here at this time?
그 여자가 이 시간에 왜 여기에 있는 걸까요?
Men?
남자?
Look at this girl
이 여자 좀 봐
Miss
미스
Your Majesty is coming. Hurry up.
폐하께서 오십니다. 서둘러요.
Good
좋음
Miss, are you back?
아가씨, 돌아오셨나요?
Even if you are only going out temporarily, you should check your appearance.
일시적으로만 외출하는 경우에도 외모를 확인해야 합니다.
What Miss?
무슨 미스?
shoes
신발
I want to see you as soon as possible
가능한 한 빨리 당신을 만나고 싶습니다
You want to use me as an excuse again?
또 나를 핑계로 삼으려는 거야?
to you
당신에게
Give it to your fiancé
약혼자에게 주세요
I just finished the funeral and my body must be very damaged.
이제 막 장례식을 마쳤는데 몸이 많이 망가졌나 봐요.
My marriage...
내 결혼...
I'm afraid your marriage will be postponed.
결혼이 연기될까봐 걱정이에요.
It should be difficult for that company to do two major events this year.
그 회사가 올해 두 가지 큰 행사를 하는 것은 어려울 것입니다.
You guys look nothing alike. You are beautiful.
너희들은 하나도 닮지 않았어 아름다우세요.
Miss
미스
why are you laughing
왜 웃고 있어?
I'm not laughing. He said he doesn't look like his brother.
나는 웃지 않는다. 그는 자신의 동생과 닮지 않았다고 말했습니다.
Not...
아니...
Not like this
이렇지 않아
No
아니요
Miss
미스
You look nothing alike
당신은 아무것도 닮지 않은 것 같아요
you are beautiful
당신은 아름답습니다
Why do you remember that sentence?
왜 그 문장이 기억나나요?
Am I so beautiful?
내가 그렇게 아름다운 걸까?
Could it be just an interjection?
그냥 감탄사일 수도 있나요?
Just like when you see a mountain, you will praise its majesty
산을 보면 그 위엄을 칭찬하는 것과 같으니라
Like praising the beauty of flowers when you see them?
꽃을 보면 꽃의 아름다움을 칭찬하는 것처럼요?
Oh my God, when were you there?
맙소사, 언제 거기 있었나요?
Start by asking and answering your own questions
스스로 질문하고 답하는 것부터 시작해 보세요.
So you heard it all?
그럼 다 들었어?
This is for you
이것은 당신을 위한 것입니다
My brother asked me to give it to you
형이 나한테 이거 주라고 했어
He also regards you as my fiancé
그 사람도 당신을 내 약혼자로 여기고 있어요
I will definitely tell him about breaking off the engagement within today.
오늘 안에 파혼에 대해 꼭 말씀드리겠습니다.
Just do it
그냥 해
You still look bad
아직도 안 좋아 보여
Laodun came in the rain the day before
라오둔은 전날 비를 맞고 왔습니다
It seems it hasn't faded yet.
아직은 시들지 않은 것 같습니다.
It's you who got it wrong. I'll take my leave first.
잘못한 건 당신이에요. 먼저 휴가를 가겠습니다.
I read that right
읽은 게 맞다
Oh my god
맙소사
Eunjo, you dress like this
은조씨 이렇게 입으세요
Are you really just like the lady from another hospital?
정말 다른 병원 아줌마랑 똑같나요?
How to tie this belt?
이 벨트를 묶는 방법은 무엇입니까?
I'm upset enough. Who is looking for me?
나는 충분히 화가 난다. 누가 나를 찾고 있나요?
Du Chengzhi’s eldest son
두청지의 장남
Do you have a problem with me...
나한테 문제가 있는 걸까...
Did you go fool around with a man last night?
어젯밤에 남자랑 장난을 쳤나요?
Men?
남자?
Did he see me with him yesterday?
그 사람이 어제 내가 그 사람과 함께 있는 걸 봤나요?
I don't know what you are talking about...
무슨 말을 하는지 모르겠어요...
He looks shameless, just like your father.
그 사람은 네 아버지처럼 뻔뻔해 보이는데.
What are you arguing about?
당신은 무엇에 대해 논쟁하고 있습니까?
Dad
아빠
I saw that stinky girl fooling around with a man yesterday
어제 그 냄새나는 여자가 남자랑 장난치는 걸 봤어
Take this seriously
이것을 진지하게 받아들이십시오
Even Du Chengzhi was involved.
Du Chengzhi도 참여했습니다.
Wait
잠깐
Du Chengzhi's eldest son goes in and out of the palace's official offices every day
두성지의 큰아들은 매일 궁궐 관청을 드나들고 있다
There's no way you don't recognize my face.
당신이 내 얼굴을 알아보지 못할 리가 없어요.
Do I have to answer such a base suspicion?
그런 근본적인 의심에 답해야 합니까?
How dare you...
어떻게 감히...
As a gentleman, even if you are suspicious
신사로서 의심스러워도
We should first ask clearly the cause and effect of the matter.
먼저 문제의 원인과 결과를 명확하게 물어봐야 합니다.
The person I met last night was the young master of my house
어젯밤에 만난 사람은 우리 집 젊은 주인이었어.
Who did you mistake for him?
그 사람을 누구로 착각했나요?
Have you not even confirmed who it is?
누구인지도 확인하지 않았나요?
I didn't have time to confirm this.
이것을 확인할 시간이 없었습니다.
But this stinky girl ran outside in the middle of the night and I just...
그런데 이 냄새나는 여자가 한밤중에 밖으로 뛰쳐나갔고 난 그냥...
Who are you calling a stinky girl?
냄새나는 여자 누구한테 전화하는 거야?
Although I have a low status, I am your elder in the family tree.
나는 지위가 낮지만 여러분의 가계에서는 장남입니다.
This is too much to say
이건 말이 너무 많아
Not to mention humiliating me like this
이렇게 나를 모욕하는 건 말할 것도 없고
It's disrespectful to the deceased
고인에게 무례한 일이다
As a scholar-official, you must know better than me, right?
학자로서 저보다 더 잘 아시겠죠?
Even in the royal family of this country
이 나라의 왕실에서도
If the evil girl enters the harem
나쁜 여자가 하렘에 들어오면
He will also receive the title and courtesy he deserves.
그는 또한 그에 합당한 칭호와 예우를 받게 될 것입니다.
What is your attitude?
당신의 태도는 무엇입니까?
You have no sense of proportion, woman
비례감이 없네 여자야
Don't act rashly
함부로 행동하지 마세요
ok dad
알았어 아빠
That's absolutely right
그것은 절대적으로 맞습니다
Observe due etiquette
예의를 지키세요
The sincerity that should have shown filial piety by the father's side
아버지 곁에서 효도를 보여야 했던 진심
Just spend the rest of your life living up to his virtues.
남은 인생을 그분의 미덕에 부응하며 보내십시오.
Cheng Cheng, hurry up and prepare to enter the palace with me.
쳉쳉, 서둘러 나와 함께 궁전에 들어갈 준비를 해라.
Yes
예
Just wait and see
그냥 기다려 봐
Just let your horse come over
그냥 말이 오도록 놔두세요
Do you dare to move this body and give it a try?
감히 이 몸을 움직여서 시험해 볼 수 있나요?
Once that happens, you're waiting to be beheaded.
그런 일이 발생하면 참수되기를 기다리고 있습니다.
what do you want to do
너는 무엇을 하고 싶니?
I want to talk to my grandson
손자와 얘기하고 싶어요
Because the men in the house
집에 남자들이 있기 때문에
They don’t seem to understand the ethical norms that should be applied to elders
노인들에게 적용되어야 할 윤리적 규범을 이해하지 못하는 것 같습니다.
So I'm here to teach you. Listen to me clearly.
그래서 나는 당신을 가르치기 위해 여기에 있습니다. 내 말을 분명히 들어보세요.
If I dare to say it to this face in the future,
앞으로 내가 감히 이 얼굴로 이렇게 말한다면,
"She's just an evil girl", "She's just a concubine"
"그냥 나쁜 여자야", "그냥 첩일 뿐이야"
Or trample or threaten life
아니면 짓밟거나 생명을 위협하거나
If you dare to say any of the above
위의 어느 하나라도 감히 말하면
Will cause trouble
문제를 일으킬 것이다
I was going to trample on you severely
널 심하게 짓밟으려고 했어
But you don’t even have that value
하지만 넌 그런 가치조차 없어
what did you say
뭐라고 했어?
I understand
나는 이해한다
The reason why you concealed your husband’s identity and insisted on getting married
남편의 정체를 숨기고 결혼을 고집한 이유
It's all for a reason
다 이유가 있는 거야
You already knew he would pass away
당신은 그가 세상을 떠날 것이라는 것을 이미 알고 있었습니다
Actually, you want to act like a lady from another hall, right?
사실 다른 홀 아줌마처럼 행동하고 싶잖아요?
Yes, whatever you say
응, 뭐라고 해도
Shen Qing makes a deal with himself
Shen Qing은 자신과 거래를 합니다.
It’s not for the sake of my father’s 300 shi as an offering of rice.
아버지의 300시를 쌀로 공양하기 위한 것이 아닙니다.
It's the name of the wife of Du Chengzhi's house.
Du Chengzhi 집 아내의 이름입니다.
His wealth and fame
그의 부와 명성
Just want to jump up the status
그냥 상태를 뛰어오르고 싶어
Too cliche and boring
너무 진부하고 지루함
Listen, grandson
들어봐, 손자야
I'm not talking about identity
나는 정체성에 대해 말하는 것이 아닙니다
It's about the etiquette of treating people.
사람을 대하는 예절에 관한 것입니다.
Why can’t you understand such a simple truth?
왜 이렇게 단순한 진리를 이해하지 못합니까?
Forget it, my thoughts about my grandson
잊어버려 내 손자에 대한 내 생각
Not interested, let alone admonishing
관심도 없고 훈계는커녕
Just follow basic etiquette from now on.
이제부터 기본적인 에티켓을 지켜주세요.
You will eventually be like them
당신도 결국 그들처럼 될 것이다
Just dress up like this and show it to that man.
이렇게 차려입고 그 남자한테 보여주면 됩니다.
It might make him more impressed with you
그 사람이 당신에게 더 깊은 인상을 받을 수도 있어요
Men?
남자?
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
Are there other men?
다른 남자도 있나요?
Help me pass it on to the concubine
첩에게 물려줄 수 있게 도와주세요
Also say hello to me by the way
그런데 나한테도 안부를 전해줘
The Concubine has given you orders today. Please come to the atrium to say hello.
오늘 첩이 당신에게 명령을 내렸습니다. 아트리움으로 오셔서 인사해주세요.
Compared with sweets like medicine and fruit
약이나 과일 같은 과자에 비해
It would be better to eat some jujubes
대추를 좀 먹으면 더 좋을 것 같아요
My mother's constitution is cold, eating this will help.
우리 엄마 체질이 차가우신데 이거 먹으면 도움이 될 것 같아요.
I heard that you go to the inner hospital every morning
아침마다 내과병원에 간다고 들었어
Are you still making medicine for me?
아직도 나를 위해 약을 만들고 있나요?
yes
예
What ridiculous thing do you want to do again?
또 무슨 말도 안 되는 일을 하고 싶나요?
I just want to completely clear up your misunderstanding
난 단지 너의 오해를 완전히 풀고 싶을 뿐이야
Misunderstanding?
오해?
About the son...
아들에 대해서...
No, I mean the misunderstanding about me
아니, 나에 대한 오해를 말하는 거야
I'm not as depraved as you fear, nor am I a scoundrel.
나는 당신이 두려워하는 것만큼 타락하지도 않았고, 악당도 아닙니다.
Although I always like to fool around
나는 항상 바보짓을 좋아하지만
Occasionally bluffing
가끔 허세를 부리는 경우
Once you become obsessed with something, you will become stubborn and have a bit of a prince's disease.
한번 뭔가에 집착하게 되면 고집이 세지고 약간 왕자병에 걸리게 됩니다.
But I am a prince, and strictly speaking, it is not a disease.
하지만 나는 왕자이고 엄밀히 말하면 질병은 아니다.
All in all
전체적으로
I also know how to show generosity to the poor
나는 또한 가난한 사람들에게 자비를 베푸는 방법도 알고 있습니다.
Occasionally, I am willing to show kindness
가끔은 친절을 베풀고 싶은 마음도 있어요
Able to accept rejection from others calmly
타인의 거절을 침착하게 받아들일 수 있음
Will also pray for the other person’s well-being
또한 상대방의 안녕을 위해 기도할 것입니다.
He also knows how to hide his difficulties for others and...
그는 또한 다른 사람들에게 자신의 어려움을 숨기는 방법도 알고 있습니다.
You really know how to praise yourself
당신은 자신을 칭찬할 줄 정말 잘 알고 있어요.
After all, complimenting yourself is the same as complimenting you, right?
결국 자신을 칭찬하는 것은 자신을 칭찬하는 것과 같죠?
All thanks to the great concubine’s teachings.
다 대첩님의 가르침 덕분이에요.
Only in this way can we raise such an excellent son
그래야만 이렇게 훌륭한 아들을 키울 수 있다
Do you know it now?
이제 알았나요?
So annoying
너무 짜증나
It seems that the mood of being a mother is the same.
엄마가 된 기분도 마찬가지인 것 같아요.
That’s the end of the grounding.
접지의 끝입니다.
Will you also accept morning greetings from your children in the future?
앞으로도 아이들의 아침인사도 받아주실 건가요?
Jinshang Palace
진상궁
Immediately order Judge Xu to bring the child
즉시 Xu 판사에게 아이를 데려오라고 명령하세요.
Who does empress refer to?
황후는 누구를 가리키는가?
Palace Maid Hong Shi
궁녀 홍시
Can't we say that Hong Shi has been expelled from the palace?
홍시가 궁궐에서 쫓겨났다고 할 수는 없지 않은가?
If the empress uses her wife to find her,
황후가 아내를 이용해 그녀를 찾아낸다면,
things will get more complicated
상황은 더욱 복잡해질 것이다
I'd better leave the palace and bring him here.
나는 궁전을 떠나 그를 여기로 데려오는 것이 좋겠다.
No
아니요
It's an emergency. Let's act together.
긴급 상황입니다. 함께 행동합시다.
Sir
선생님
She doesn't seem to be in another courtyard
그녀는 다른 안뜰에 있는 것 같지 않습니다.
Where did he go?
到底跑去哪里了
Dazao, go to the Huimin Office and have a look
다자오, 희민 사무실에 가서 좀 봐
yes
응
The young master will not return until the garrison period
젊은 주인은 수비 기간까지 돌아오지 않습니다.
Is it okay for you to stay so late?
이렇게 늦게까지 머물러도 괜찮습니까?
It's okay. Everyone in the house has gone out.
괜찮아요. 집에 있던 사람들이 모두 나갔습니다.
I have some things that I want to discuss with the young master
젊은 스승님과 상의하고 싶은 것이 몇 가지 있습니다.
Is anyone here?
여기 누구 있어요?
This voice…
이 목소리는…
what are you doing here
여기서 뭐해?
Are you?
당신은요?
I'm Dayi's school friend
저는 다이의 학교 친구예요
So that's it
그래서 그게 다야
What should we do? Our young master is out.
우리는 무엇을 해야 합니까? 우리 젊은 주인님이 나갔어요.
He should be here to find me
그 사람은 나를 찾으러 여기 있어야 해
How did you find this place?
이 장소를 어떻게 찾았나요?
Enzu
엔즈
How can you address the young master's friends as "you"?
어떻게 젊은 스승의 친구들을 "당신"이라고 부를 수 있습니까?
It doesn't matter. We always get along casually.
그것은 중요하지 않습니다. 우리는 항상 아무렇지도 않게 지내요.
What?
무엇?
You'll scare people if you say that.
그렇게 말하면 사람들이 겁을 먹게 될 거예요.
Because I often go in and out of the Huimin Office
저는 희민 사무실에 자주 드나들기 때문에
We are old acquaintances with her
우리는 그녀와 오랜 친분이 있다
That's it
그게 다야
What's the matter with you coming to me?
나한테 오는 게 무슨 문제야?
Sir, someone is looking for Hong Shi
선생님, 누군가 홍시를 찾고 있어요
Who is Hong Shi?
홍시는 누구인가?
Is the palace maid Hong Shi?
궁녀 홍시인가?
I'll come to your door for this name.
나는 이 이름을 위해 당신의 집에 갈 것입니다.
You should be able to guess who is looking for her, right?
누가 그녀를 찾고 있는지 짐작할 수 있어야겠죠?
What should I do? It’s time for me to go.
어떻게 해야 하나요? 이제 갈 시간이에요.
Okay, let’s eat old hens next time
알았어, 다음에는 늙은 암탉을 먹자
Wait
잠깐
Just wait for me and bring this with you
날 기다리고 이걸 가지고 와
Why is the Queen Mother looking for me?
태후께서 왜 나를 찾으시나요?
How would I know?
내가 어떻게 알 수 있나요?
Instead, why did you come to my house to catch the old hen?
그런데 왜 우리 집에 늙은 암탉을 잡으러 왔나요?
Mom insists on catching the old hen and giving it to me
엄마는 늙은 암탉을 잡아서 나에게 주겠다고 고집하신다.
how can i refuse
어떻게 거절할 수 있어?
Don't call it so smoothly, okay?
너무 쉽게 부르지 마세요, 알았죠?
Why is such a good thing put in the cabinet and not taken away?
왜 이렇게 좋은 것을 캐비닛에 넣어두고 꺼내지 않는 걸까요?
Still collected neatly
그래도 깔끔하게 모아놨다
No
아니요
Wait
잠깐
This is…
이것은…
Oops
이런
Do I really have that?
나한테 정말 그런 게 있는 걸까?
Are they really collected neatly?
정말 깔끔하게 정리되어 있죠?
Mom...that's not right
엄마...그건 안 돼요
This should be something your daughter left intentionally
이건 당신 딸이 일부러 두고 간 게 틀림없어요
Why take it out?
왜 꺼내나요?
Really?
정말?
Take it well. Give it to me.
잘 받아라. 나에게 주세요.
I want to wear
입고 싶다
I really don’t know who picked it.
정말 누가 뽑았는지 모르겠어요.
You really have a first-class vision
당신은 정말 일류의 비전을 가지고 있습니다.
Where are the lotus leaves put aside?
연잎은 어디에 넣어두나요?
Are even the lotus leaves carefully dried and preserved?
연잎도 잘 말려서 보존하고 있나요?
I feel like it’s something you cherish, so I didn’t throw it away and kept it.
소중한 물건인 것 같아서 버리지 않고 보관했어요.
No matter how you look at it, right?
아무리 봐도 그렇죠?
My mother also thinks I cherish it, right?
우리 엄마도 내가 그걸 소중하게 생각하는 것 같죠?
Not really
별로
That comes with the embroidered shoes
자수 신발과 함께 제공됩니다.
Why are you shouting with that straight face?
왜 그렇게 무표정한 얼굴로 소리를 지르는 거야?
Didn’t you see that my mother was scared by you?
우리 엄마가 너 때문에 무서워하는 거 못 봤어?
Apologize immediately
즉시 사과하세요
Sorry
미안
It doesn't matter
그것은 중요하지 않습니다
Why is your child like this?
당신의 아이는 왜 이런가요?
Just keep this lotus leaf
이 연잎만 간직하세요
After all, it seems to be an extremely precious thing
그러고 보면 정말 소중한 물건인 것 같아요
That…
그…
Why don't you go out first?
먼저 나가보는 게 어때?
Is it convenient for me to take a step to talk?
한발짝 다가가서 이야기하는 것이 편리한가요?
do you have anything to say to me
나한테 할 말 있어?
It's our first time meeting. It's a little offensive to say this.
우리의 첫 만남이에요. 이렇게 말하는 것은 조금 공격적입니다.
It may also be a little abrupt
조금 갑작스러울 수도 있어요
But for now you...
하지만 지금은 당신이...
Is it better to keep distance from Ling Qianjin?
Ling Qianjin과 거리를 두는 것이 더 낫습니까?
Is it because a married daughter is an outsider after all?
결혼한 딸은 결국 아웃사이더이기 때문일까?
What?
무엇?
Yes exactly so
네 바로 그렇습니다
If she always runs to her parents’ house
만약 그녀가 항상 부모님 집으로 달려간다면
What would your in-laws think?
시댁 식구들은 어떻게 생각하실까요?
That's right
그렇죠
I'm too greedy
욕심이 너무 많아요
I didn't notice it when she stayed with me before
그녀가 전에 나와 함께 있었을 때 난 그걸 눈치채지 못했어
Now that I'm married, I want to keep her by my side even more.
이제 결혼했으니 더욱 그녀를 곁에 두고 싶다.
me too
나도
What?
무엇?
I mean, Ling Qianjin probably thinks the same way.
내 말은, Ling Qianjin도 아마 같은 방식으로 생각할 것입니다.
Anyway, I will follow your advice
어쨌든 나는 당신의 조언을 따르겠습니다
Keep a little more distance from her
그녀와 조금 더 거리를 두세요
Just temporarily, just all of a sudden
그냥 일시적으로, 갑자기
I'm so sorry
정말 미안해요
I suddenly thought of my mother
문득 엄마가 생각났어요
Really?
정말요?
By the way, never kill any old hen casually.
그건 그렇고, 늙은 암탉을 함부로 죽이지 마십시오.
Give it to your daughter
딸에게 줘
Come back, that's mine
돌아와, 그건 내 꺼야
Really, there is no difference between you and me.
사실, 당신과 나 사이에는 차이가 없습니다.
what is our relationship
우리 관계가 뭐야?
This is the current situation
이것이 현재 상황이다
What's mine is yours
내 것은 당신 것이에요
What's yours is mine
당신의 것은 내 것입니다
After changing the body
몸을 바꾼 후
There is always a feeling of treasure hunting
항상 보물찾기 같은 느낌이 있어요
What this body hides
이 몸이 무엇을 숨기고 있는지
I dug them out one by one
하나하나 파헤쳐봤는데
What's next?
다음은 무엇입니까?
There is no such thing
그런 건 없어요
And those embroidered shoes
그리고 저 자수 신발
I just thought it was a pity to lose it, so I put it away.
그냥 잃어버리면 안타깝다고 생각해서 치워두었어요.
I think so too
나도 그렇게 생각해요
I want to go back to the place now
이제 그 자리로 돌아가고 싶다
It's up to you to decide whether you want to go to the atrium or not.
아트리움에 갈 것인지 말 것인지 결정하는 것은 당신에게 달려 있습니다.
bow your head
머리를 숙여라
Damn it, Your Majesty
젠장, 폐하
Du Chengzhi, long time no see
Du Chengzhi, 오랜만이군요
How are you doing?
잘 지내세요?
I have heard that your father passed away
네 아버지가 돌아가셨다는 소식을 들었어
He must have been exhausted after being bedridden for many years.
그는 수년 동안 침대에 누워 지냈기 때문에 지쳤을 것입니다.
I sincerely hope that he will no longer be tortured
그가 더 이상 고문당하지 않기를 진심으로 바랍니다.
have you ever met my father
우리 아버지를 만난 적이 있나요?
I just heard that he was ill
방금 그 사람이 아프다는 소식을 들었어
I can't thank you enough
도저히 감사할 수가 없어요
I heard that your Majesty entered His Majesty’s bedroom last night.
폐하께서 어젯밤에 폐하의 침실에 들어가셨다는 소식을 들었습니다.
Correct excessive use of medicinal materials
약재의 과도한 사용을 바로잡는다
There is such a thing
그런 게 있어요
I am the deputy promotion officer of the internal hospital and have great responsibilities.
저는 내부병원 홍보차장으로서 막중한 책임을 맡고 있습니다.
The imperial doctor will be interrogated strictly
황실 의사는 엄중하게 심문을 받을 것이다
It doesn't have to be that way. I didn't mean it.
꼭 그렇게 될 필요는 없습니다. 그런 뜻은 아니었어요.
It's not a big deal. Just ask.
그것은 큰 문제가 아니다. 그냥 물어보세요.
obey
복종하다
So be it
그러니 그렇게 해라
I'm leaving first
나 먼저 갈게
Your Majesty's maid, please stay.
폐하의 하녀님, 머물러 주십시오.
Yours fell off
네 것이 떨어졌어
give it to me
나에게 줘
Why do you need adults to help you...
왜 어른들의 도움이 필요합니까?
maid
하녀
Didn't you hear us?
우리 말 못 들었어?
The golden palace lady will go to the concubine's palace immediately to see you if there is something urgent.
금궁녀는 급한 일이 있으면 즉시 후궁으로 가서 당신을 만나러 갈 것입니다.
Yes
예
Please go back to the dormitory
기숙사로 돌아가주세요
good
좋아
The Maharaja seems not to know much about the incense.
마하라자는 향에 대해 잘 모르는 것 같습니다.
All agree
모두 동의한다
Can you tell me the names of the medicinal materials introduced from the Ming Dynasty?
명나라 때부터 전래된 약재의 이름을 알려주실 수 있나요?
Why do you ask this?
왜 이런 걸 물어보나요?
I want to understand and learn about it by the way
그런데 나는 그것을 이해하고 배우고 싶다.
Maybe it will be useful in the future
아마 앞으로도 유용할 것 같아요
That's madder, the seed of a flower
더 이상하네요, 꽃의 씨앗이군요
It is a medicinal material that was only available in the Ming Dynasty
명나라에서만 구할 수 있었던 약재입니다.
madder
더 미치게
thank you
감사합니다
I heard that you have something to do with your little girl
나는 당신이 당신의 어린 딸과 관련이 있다고 들었습니다
I came to you to praise you for your efforts last time.
지난번에 당신의 노력을 칭찬하기 위해 당신에게 왔습니다.
By the way...
그런데...
I think you have another topic.
다른 주제가 있는 것 같아요.
Not bad
나쁘지 않아요
Not only are you quick with your hands and feet, you are also quite sharp.
당신은 손과 발이 빠를 뿐만 아니라, 꽤 날카롭습니다.
From now on, you can monitor the Maharaja for me.
이제부터 마하라자를 대신해서 모니터링해 주실 수 있습니다.
Surveillance?
감시?
Then you really found the right person.
그렇다면 당신은 정말로 적합한 사람을 찾았습니다.
Especially his relationship with women
특히 여자와의 관계는
Also help me investigate secretly
비밀리에 조사하는 것도 도와주세요
A grown-up woman?
다 자란 여자?
Follow your orders, I will observe closely and pay more attention
당신의 명령을 따르십시오. 나는 면밀히 관찰하고 더 많은 관심을 기울일 것입니다.
This incident makes me very uneasy
이 사건은 나를 매우 불안하게 만든다
I'm worried about him hanging out all day
그 사람이 하루종일 놀고 있어서 걱정돼요
Will you meet some untouchables with no family background or background?
가족 배경이나 배경이 없는 불가촉천민을 만날 것인가?
Concubine
첩
What you just said
방금 말한 것
I hope you are in front of the Maharaja
마하라자 앞에 있기를 바라요
Never mention
언급하지 마세요
what did you say
뭐라고 했어?
Right
오른쪽
That child is rebellious
그 아이는 반항적이야
The more forbidden it is, the more he wants to resist
금지할수록 그는 더 저항하고 싶어한다
You know Maharaja very well
마하라자를 잘 아시네요
one more thing
한 가지 더
Find out who is the woman holding hands with him in the courtyard
마당에서 그와 손을 잡고 있는 여자가 누구인지 알아보세요
If I tell my brother
내가 형한테 말하면
This confirms the impression that women are thoughtless and act rashly.
이는 여성이 경솔하고 경솔하게 행동한다는 인상을 확증해준다.
Please also ask the empress of the middle temple to help me.
그리고 중사황후께도 도움을 청하시기 바랍니다.
It just so happens that I am also opposed to marrying into the Du Chengzhi family.
공교롭게도 나 역시 두승지 가문과 결혼하는 것을 반대합니다.
Things take a turn for the better
상황은 좋은 방향으로 흘러간다
I will find another time to tell him
나는 그에게 말할 다른 시간을 찾을 것이다
thank you
감사합니다
Hailin, have you really decided?
헤일린 씨, 정말 결정하셨나요?
A woman regrets her marriage
결혼을 후회하는 여자
But I will be tortured by the rumors for a long time
하지만 나는 오랫동안 소문에 시달릴 것이다
I'm willing to suffer the consequences
나는 그 결과를 기꺼이 감수할 것이다.
Why hasn't he come yet?
그 사람은 왜 아직 안 왔어요?
Your Majesty, Hong Shi is back
폐하, 홍시가 돌아왔습니다
Let her in quickly
빨리 들여보내줘
What did the concubine say?
첩이 뭐라고 말했습니까?
Let’s talk later. I’m so tired.
나중에 얘기하자. 너무 피곤해요.
You didn't make any mistake with my face, right?
내 얼굴에 실수한 건 아니지?
what do you know
당신은 무엇을 알고 있나요
Use your little body to run around all day long
작은 몸으로 하루 종일 뛰어다녀
This is really no ordinary tiredness
이건 정말 평범한 피로가 아니야
That's my body and I know it, okay?
그건 내 몸이고 나도 그걸 알아, 알았지?
Stop pretending and get up quickly
척은 그만하고 빨리 일어나
Falling asleep so quickly?
너무 빨리 잠들었나요?
It seems that he is really tired
그 사람 정말 피곤한 것 같아.
This…
이…
I accepted it
나는 그것을 받아들였다
(when hands are put together)
(손을 모을 때)
(The moment you longed for came true)
(당신이 바랐던 순간이 현실이 되었습니다)
(I'll call again)
(다시 전화할게요)
(What I miss, what I treasure)
(그리운 것, 소중히 여기는 것)
(your love)
(당신의 사랑)
(Those are very beautiful)
(정말 아름다워요)
(A day that cannot be erased)
(지울 수 없는 하루)
(going against time)
(시간을 거슬러가며)
(Come to the place where we first met)
(우리 처음 만났던 곳으로 와)
(You're my everything to me)
(당신은 나에게 전부입니다)
(The one that attracted me)
(나를 매료시킨 사람)
(named your dazzling sunshine to me)
(나에게 당신의 눈부신 햇살이라 이름을 지어주었어요)
(The moment I see you again)
(다시 만나는 순간)
(My heart is calling you)
(내 마음이 널 부르고 있어)
(We Again Again)
(우리 또 다시)
Don't move
움직이지 마세요
My face turns out to be so pretty
얼굴이 너무 예쁜 것 같아요
Don't interrupt my appreciation
내 감사를 방해하지 마세요
at least this moment
적어도 지금 이 순간은
I don't think soul swapping is that bad
영혼교환이 그렇게 나쁜건 아닌거 같은데
that night
그날 밤
I said I would catch you with my own hands
내 손으로 널 잡겠다고 했어
not sincere
성실하지 않다
No
아니요
you have to mean it
진심으로 해야 해
the things i did
내가 한 일들
Just because I care too much
내가 너무 신경을 쓴다고 해서
Watching those patients starving, medicine doesn’t work
환자들이 굶어죽는 걸 보니 약이 효과가 없네
I couldn't sit back and watch, so I started doing it.
가만히 앉아서 볼 수가 없어서 시작하게 됐어요.
You must not understand
이해하면 안 된다
Me too
나도
Why am I like this?
내가 왜 이럴까?
I can't think of an answer even if I try hard.
열심히 노력해도 답이 생각나지 않네요.
so i decided
그래서 내가 결정했어
Just think that God asked me to mind my own business.
하나님께서 나에게 내 일에 전념하라고 하셨다고 생각해 보십시오.
This way I don't have to look for reasons anymore
이렇게 하면 더 이상 이유를 찾을 필요가 없습니다.
I feel more comfortable
좀 더 편해진 것 같아요
not for anyone
누구에게도 아닌
Just to make myself feel better
그냥 기분이 좋아지려고
Very selfish, right?
아주 이기적이죠?
maybe
어쩌면
It's a kind of vanity, right?
일종의 허영심이죠?
That's what you want
그것이 당신이 원하는 것입니다
you really mean it
정말 진심이야
About what you promised me before
예전에 나한테 약속했던 일에 대해서
Please stay within my range from now on.
이제부터 내 범위 안에 있어주세요.
within my control
내 통제하에
But if you go beyond this range
하지만 이 범위를 벗어나면
Moving to the foundation of North Korea
북한의 기초로 나아가다
I will definitely catch you
꼭 잡아줄게
But we can't usher in that day
하지만 우리는 그 날을 맞이할 수 없습니다
How could there be
어떻게 그럴 수가 있지?
A little thief who steals things everywhere
여기저기서 물건을 훔치는 작은 도둑
Why should we shake the foundation of this country?
왜 이 나라의 기초를 흔들어야 합니까?
I promise you too
나도 약속해요
If one day I have to be captured
언젠가 내가 잡혀야 한다면
It will definitely be done by the Maharaja himself
반드시 마하라자가 직접 할 것이다.
Your Majesty, Judge Xu requests an audience.
폐하, 쉬 판사님, 청중을 요청합니다.
let him in
그를 들여 보내줘
Quick position change
빠른 위치 변경
Is it because I don’t know how to observe words and emotions? Did I come in too early?
말과 감정을 관찰하는 방법을 모르기 때문일까요? 내가 너무 일찍 들어왔나?
Well, from now on, count to ten at the door before coming in.
자, 이제부터 들어오기 전에 문앞에서 10까지 세세요.
Yeah
응
What did Du Chengzhi say just now?
방금 Du Chengzhi가 뭐라고 말했습니까?
Have you entered His Highness's bedroom?
전하의 침실에 들어가셨나요?
Right
오른쪽
When we met a few days ago
며칠 전에 만났을 때
I forgot to tell you this
나는 당신에게 이것을 말하는 것을 잊었다
Dad, do you think the Maharaja wants to test you?
아빠, 마하라자가 당신을 시험하고 싶어한다고 생각하세요?
It seems not to me
내가 보기엔 아닌 것 같아
I think the same thing as you
나도 너랑 같은 생각이야
Then why are you so concerned
그럼 왜 그렇게 걱정하는 거야?
Lord Daoyue…
다오웨 선생님…
This title is interesting
이 제목이 흥미롭네요
Did you let them take the medicinal materials?
약재를 가져가게 놔두셨나요?
No wonder Du Chengzhi and Zhang Shurong mentioned my title last time
Du Chengzhi와 Zhang Shurong이 지난번에 내 제목을 언급한 것도 당연합니다.
Because His Highness was not angry
전하께서는 화내지 않으셨기 때문에
I think we should get through this smoothly.
내 생각엔 이 일을 순조롭게 이겨내야 할 것 같아.
That's how those people talk
그 사람들은 그렇게 얘기해요.
Even if the speaker has no intention
말하는 사람의 의도가 없더라도
But people around me always think there is something more than what is meant.
하지만 내 주변 사람들은 항상 의미하는 것보다 더 많은 것이 있다고 생각합니다.
It seems that being a king is not an easy task.
왕이 되는 것은 쉬운 일이 아닌 것 같습니다.
Just fold a quilt
이불 좀 접어주세요
It will alarm everyone in the house
집에 있는 모든 사람에게 경고할 것입니다.
Just asking for the name of the medicine
약 이름만 물어보면
We need to bring in those imperial doctors for interrogation.
심문을 위해 저 황실 의사들을 불러와야 합니다.
We are all the same. We cannot be willful in our words and deeds.
우리는 모두 똑같습니다. 우리는 말과 행동에 있어 고집을 부리면 안 됩니다.
You shouldn't say that in front of someone who is suddenly a young widow.
갑자기 젊은 과부가 된 사람 앞에서 그런 말을 해서는 안 됩니다.
Not necessarily
꼭 그런 것은 아니다
My husband’s family is kinder than expected
남편 가족은 생각보다 친절해요
Really?
정말요?
Impossible
불가능하다
I will enjoy the treatment that a lady deserves in another courtyard
나는 다른 안뜰에서 여성이 마땅히 받아야 할 대우를 즐길 것입니다
don't worry about me
나에 대해 걱정하지 마세요
Let’s not mention this first
이건 먼저 언급하지 말자
His Highness must be in a panic.
전하께서는 당황하셨을 것입니다.
His younger brother suddenly showed great concern for him
그의 남동생이 갑자기 그에게 큰 관심을 보였습니다.
What kind of medicine did you just say?
방금 무슨 약이라고 하셨나요?
That's called madder
그거 매더라고 하는데
Is His Highness also getting old?
전하도 늙어가나요?
Looks like he's getting sicker and sicker
점점 더 아픈 것 같아
Are you feeling uncomfortable somewhere?
어딘가 불편하신가요?
The body suddenly becomes very heavy
갑자기 몸이 무거워진다.
how can you get sick
어떻게 아플 수 있니?
Lately, every day has been no different from usual.
최근에는 매일이 평소와 다르지 않았습니다.
Except that I haven’t lit any incense these past few days.
다만 나는 지난 며칠간 향을 전혀 피우지 않았다.
Light up the incense
향을 켜세요
The Lord gradually began to show symptoms of addiction
주님은 점차 중독 증상을 보이기 시작하셨습니다.
Since the king entered the bedroom on purpose,
왕이 일부러 침실에 들어왔기 때문에,
Your Majesty won't sit idly by and ignore it, right?
폐하께서 멍하니 앉아 계실 리가 없겠죠?
Since the day when the secret records were handed over to His Highness,
비밀기록이 전하께 인계된 날부터
Your majesty keeps getting in my way for some reason
폐하께서 무슨 이유인지 자꾸 방해하시네요
Do you want to get rid of him quietly?
조용히 그 사람을 없애고 싶나요?
If you are not careful, all your efforts will be wasted.
조심하지 않으면 이전의 모든 노력이 물거품이 될 것입니다.
After all, His Highness believes that the royal family is sacred and inviolable
결국, 전하께서는 왕실이 신성하고 침해할 수 없는 존재라고 믿습니다.
Reason
이유
I need a reason
이유가 필요해
It seems that we need to carefully search the whereabouts of the Maharaja.
마하라자의 행방을 주의깊게 수색해야 할 것 같습니다.
Can't let go of even the slightest sound of wind
작은 바람 소리도 놓칠 수 없어
I understand
나는 이해한다
I'm not ordering you
나는 당신에게 명령하지 않습니다
Since we want to force the king to submit,
Since we want to force the king to submit,
It might be dangerous. You'd better stay out of it.
위험할 수도 있습니다. 당신은 그것을 멀리하는 것이 좋습니다.
Then who should be responsible for this matter?
그렇다면 이 문제는 누가 책임져야 할까요?
I obviously want to enter Si Xian Mansion
나는 분명히 Si Xian Mansion에 들어가고 싶다
But he was sent to Yijin Mansion
하지만 그는 이진맨션으로 보내졌다.
It is said that Du Chengzhi made some moves
Du Chengzhi가 몇 가지 움직임을 보였다고합니다.
Si Xianfu?
Si Xianfu?
Are you there to supervise the corruption of high-ranking officials?
고위공직자들의 비리를 감시하기 위해 거기 있는 겁니까?
Or do you want to capture the country’s scholar-bureaucrats?
아니면 그 나라의 학자 관료들을 붙잡고 싶나요?
Above them?
그 위에?
It seems that I really should do this
이건 꼭 해봐야 할 것 같다
You don't have that qualification
당신은 그런 자격이 없습니다
Because I never gave you this qualification
난 너한테 이런 자격을 준 적이 없으니까
You'd better not chat with the beast for too long
짐승과 너무 오랫동안 대화하지 않는 것이 좋습니다
If you have something to say, just say it.
할 말이 있으면 그냥 말하세요.
what do you think i want to say
내가 무슨 말을 하고 싶은 것 같아?
Since I was sent to Yijin Mansion
이진맨션으로 보내졌으니까
Is it the royal family?
왕실인가요?
Move them all to Yijin Mansion. Don’t leave out any one.
모두 이진맨션으로 옮겨주세요. 어느 하나도 빠뜨리지 마십시오.
Yes
예
what is this doing
이게 뭐하는 거야?
I told you just tell me what you're searching for
내가 말했잖아, 네가 뭘 찾고 있는지 말해봐
I will submit the report
보고서를 제출하겠습니다
you don't have to know
당신은 알 필요가 없습니다
Because it's confidential
기밀사항이니까
Complete the move before the deadline
마감일 이전에 이사를 완료하세요.
Yes
예
Ji Tong?
지통?
so interesting
너무 흥미롭다
Why is there a line of people there?
왜 거기에 사람들이 줄을 서 있나요?
It is said that Ji Tong is dead
지통이 죽었다고 하는데
Everyone said they wanted to give him some money so he could go on the road.
모두들 그가 여행을 떠날 수 있도록 돈을 좀 주고 싶다고 말했습니다.
It's been like that for more than ten days
열흘 넘게 그랬어요
Take it and leave it there
가져가서 거기 놔둬
This is real money. Will the beggars pick it up?
이것은 진짜 돈입니다. 거지들이 그것을 주울 것인가?
Just let them pick it up
그냥 가져가게 놔두세요
If you meet someone who is hungry
배고픈 사람을 만나면
Even if it’s money for traveling, Ji Tong will donate generously
여행비라도 지통이가 아낌없이 기부하겠습니다
Condolences?
애도?
This is what the people in the market said
시장 사람들이 하는 말이 이렇다.
Don't you go and have a look?
가서 한 번 살펴보지 않겠습니까?
Are they even mourned by the people?
그들은 심지어 사람들의 애도를 받고 있습니까?
Ji Tong is not so great that he deserves to be mourned
Ji Tong은 애도할 만큼 위대하지 않습니다
Although I am very ashamed of the deceased
비록 고인이 매우 부끄럽지만
But please go with that legendary reputation
하지만 그 전설적인 명성을 가지고 가십시오.
Go farther
더 멀리 가세요
They are all in Yijin Mansion as well.
그들도 모두 이진맨션에 있어요.
But you are the experience and I am everything
하지만 당신은 경험이고 나는 전부입니다
You are the son of the current Du Chengzhi
당신은 현재 Du Chengzhi의 아들입니다.
And I am the son of a former college student, right?
그리고 저는 전 대학생의 아들이죠?
speak clearly
명확하게 말하다
I am the top scholar in the imperial examination
나는 황실고시에서 최고 우등생이다
You are Yin Xu who came in through the back door because of your family background.
당신은 집안 배경 때문에 뒷문으로 들어온 윤서입니다.
But why do you keep hanging around here?
그런데 왜 계속 여기에 맴돌고 있는 거죠?
I want to see first what the king of this country looks like
이 나라의 왕은 어떤 모습일지 먼저 보고 싶어
Go pick him up again
가서 다시 그를 데리러 와
He has been staying in his residence for several days without coming out.
그는 며칠 동안 나오지 않고 자택에 머물렀다.
On the contrary, it is more imaginable
오히려 상상이 더 가네요
Then go and meet
그럼 가서 만나요
Wouldn't it be better if we went directly to see him?
우리가 직접 만나러 가는 게 낫지 않을까요?
A mere experience in Yijin Mansion
이진맨션에서의 단순한 경험
It’s not that easy to meet the king who is a royal family
왕족인 왕을 만나기가 쉽지 않죠
Didn't he even go to the Robbery Hall these days?
요즘은 강도회관에도 안 갔나요?
The Maharaja has recently been studying the Four Books and Five Classics again at his residence.
마하라자는 최근 자신의 집에서 다시 사서오경을 공부하고 있습니다.
four…
네…
That child hasn't touched a book since he was ten years old
그 아이는 열 살 이후로 책을 한 번도 만져본 적이 없어요
Are you feeling uncomfortable somewhere?
어딘가 불편하신가요?
It's not that he doesn't read, he just pretends not to read...
안 읽는 게 아니라, 그냥 안 읽는 척 하는 거지...
Could this be the case? Maybe it's just my delusion.
이런 일이 일어날 수 있습니까? 어쩌면 그것은 단지 나의 착각일지도 모릅니다.
Let's go and see how he looks, little one.
가서 그가 어떻게 보이는지 보자, 꼬마야.
Are they just people who look alike?
그냥 닮은 사람들일까요?
why are you here
당신은 왜 여기에 있습니까?
The empress of the middle hall will arrive at noon
중궁의 황후가 정오에 도착할 것이다
The empress ordered all the ladies to have a chat here first.
황후는 모든 귀부인들에게 먼저 이곳에서 대화를 나누라고 명령했습니다.
Yes Yes
예 예
It’s been a long time since this party
이 파티는 오랜만이야
nice to meet you all
모두 만나서 반가워요
Yes Yes
예 예
By the way, let's comfort Lady Shen.
그건 그렇고, Lady Shen을 위로합시다.
I heard she will break off the engagement soon
그 사람이 곧 약혼을 파기할 거라고 들었어
Didn't we agree to keep it a secret?
우리는 그것을 비밀로 하기로 동의하지 않았나요?
The more unfortunate something happens, the more we should all comfort each other
안타까운 일이 일어날수록 우리 모두는 서로를 위로해야 합니다.
Oh my god
맙소사
How could this happen? You must be feeling very uncomfortable.
어떻게 이런 일이 일어날 수 있습니까? 기분이 많이 불편하시겠네요.
I'm fine
난 괜찮아
Say it now
지금 말해보세요
What is the reason for breaking off the engagement?
약혼을 파기하는 이유는 무엇입니까?
That…
그…
If you don't explain it clearly at this time,
이때 명확하게 설명하지 않으면
In the end it will all be the woman’s fault
결국 다 여자 탓이겠지
It's not that you're hiding other men
다른 남자를 숨기는 게 아니야
That is to say, he is too ugly
즉, 그는 너무 못생겼다
Or the face is covered with pockmarks
아니면 얼굴이 곰보로 뒤덮여 있거나
Isn't it?
그렇지 않나요?
Lord Daoyue arrives
도월공이 도착하다
Is he the Maharaja?
그 사람이 마하라자인가요?
As the name suggests, a marriage contract is just an agreement
이름에서 알 수 있듯이 결혼 계약은 단지 합의 일뿐입니다.
Not an unbreakable taboo
깨지지 않는 금기가 아니다
So it's just breaking the agreement
그러니까 합의를 깨는 거잖아.
It can't be said to be anyone's fault.
누구의 잘못이라고 할 수도 없습니다.
Sorry for interrupting the ladies' chat.
여자들의 대화를 방해해서 미안해요.
It's just that when I passed by, it sounded really harsh.
그냥 지나갈 때 정말 거친 소리가 들렸거든요.
Long time no see, Your Majesty
오랜만입니다 폐하
do you know me
당신은 나를 아시나요
We met once before in Dafei Palace
우리는 예전에 Dafei Palace에서 한 번 만났었습니다.
That's it
그게 다야
I have no impression
인상이 없어요
rude
무례한
don't say that
그런 말 하지 마
That Miss Shen Hailin
그 미스 션 하이린(Shen Hailin)
what
뭐
If you don't mind, could you spare a moment?
괜찮으시다면 잠시 시간을 내주시겠습니까?
are you talking about me
나에 대해 말하는 거야?
Wasn't that the kind of scenario just now?
방금도 그런 시나리오 아니었나요?
The prince who appears at the moment when the heroine is in dire straits
히로인이 위기에 처한 순간에 등장하는 왕자님
what
뭐
It turns out this is really what it feels like
알고보니 정말 이런 느낌이네요
It seems that I am suitable to be a prince
나는 왕자가 되기에 적합한 것 같다
Should I come to your rescue more often?
내가 당신을 구출하러 더 자주 와야 할까요?
It seems you don't read folktales
당신은 동화를 읽지 않는 것 같습니다
No I like it very much
아니 아주 좋아해요
"The Story of Shutong" and "The Story of Princess Pinggang"
『수통이야기』와 『평강공주이야기』
"The Biography of the Pheasant" and "The Biography of Shuxiang"
『꿩전』과 『서상전』
"The Biography of Li Chunfeng" and "The Biography of Jin Shangshu"
"리춘펑 전기"와 "진상수 전기"
"Jin Shangshu Biography"?
"진상수 전기"?
That's a hard to find book
구하기 힘든 책이네요
When Xueping separated from her fiancé, who had made a century-old promise
Xueping이 100년 간의 약속을 했던 약혼자와 헤어졌을 때
I still cried like tears
난 아직도 눈물처럼 울었어
I am the reincarnation of the dead Xueping
나는 죽은 설평의 환생이다
When I return to my fiancé’s house again
다시 약혼자 집에 돌아갈 때
Can't help but cheer
응원하지 않을 수 없다
But the real essence of that book is
하지만 그 책의 진짜 본질은
Xueping, who disguised herself as a man, won a great victory in the war
남장을 한 설평은 전쟁에서 큰 승리를 거두었다.
You really are a book lover
당신은 정말 책을 사랑하는 사람이군요
It turns out you also love reading
당신도 독서를 좋아하는 것으로 나타났습니다
Are you really the Maharaja?
당신이 정말로 마하라자입니까?
This face says it all. It's amazing.
이 얼굴이 모든 것을 말해줍니다. 정말 놀랍습니다.
Previously, the little girl didn’t know the Maharaja.
이전에 그 어린 소녀는 마하라자를 몰랐습니다.
I'm really sorry
정말 미안해요
don't say that
그런 말 하지 마
I just happened to pass by
우연히 지나가다 보니
Seeing that you seemed to be in trouble, I came to help you.
당신이 곤경에 처해 있는 것 같아서 도와주러 왔습니다.
Is it too rash?
너무 성급한가?
No
아니요
you are at the right time
당신은 적절한 시간에 있습니다
Come at the right pace
적절한 속도로 오세요
Actually, I also have something to apologize to you for.
사실 나도 너한테 사과할 일이 있어.
I unintentionally gave you a bad reputation
본의 아니게 네게 나쁜 평판을 주었지
Don't you ask what it is?
그것이 무엇인지 묻지 않습니까?
you will at the right time
너는 적절한 때에 그럴 것이다
Give me an appropriate explanation
적절한 설명을 해주세요
thank you for your understanding
이해해주셔서 감사합니다
I will tell you everything later
나중에 다 말해줄게
let me go
날 보내줘
I tell you to let go
놓으라고 하네
Who is this?
이 사람은 누구입니까?
Abominable
혐오스러운
Meet here again
여기서 다시 만나요
Does Your Majesty also know Master Zai Yi?
폐하께서는 자이이(Zai Yi) 스승님도 알고 계십니까?
That…
그…
Maharaja?
마하라자?
I finally understand why you show up here dressed like this
네가 왜 이런 옷을 입고 여기 왔는지 드디어 이해가 가네
That's a misunderstanding
그건 오해에요
Experience from the Fourth Rank Yijin Mansion
4등 이진저택 체험
Facing a monarch who is not restricted by official rank
관직의 제약을 받지 않는 군주와 마주하다
But he still stood still. Is that disloyal to the court?
그러나 그는 여전히 가만히 서 있었습니다. 그것은 법원에 대한 불충성입니까?
shut up
닥쳐
If I hadn't been wearing this face now, you would have died a long time ago
지금 이 얼굴을 하고 있지 않았다면 당신은 오래 전에 죽었을 거예요.
what's going on
무슨 일이야?
The experience of Yijinfu Ren Zaiyi
Yijinfu Ren Zaiyi의 경험
Meet Your Majesty
폐하를 만나보세요
soon after
곧
We will definitely meet again
우리는 꼭 다시 만날 거예요
I want to go back and take care of my family first
돌아가서 가족부터 먼저 챙기고 싶다
I'll take my leave now.
나는 이제 떠날 것이다.
You follow me
당신은 나를 따라
Just wait and be patient
그냥 기다려 인내심을 가지세요
Don't make a big deal out of it
그것으로 큰 일을 만들지 마십시오
Sir, who is the person who left with Hong Shi?
선생님, 홍시와 함께 떠난 사람은 누구입니까?
Sure enough, it's still somewhat useful.
물론, 여전히 어느 정도 유용합니다.
Sir
선생님
Calculating the time, Hong Shiying has arrived at Du Chengzhi's residence.
시간을 계산해 보니 홍시영은 두성지의 집에 도착했다.
if i come forward
내가 앞으로 오면
things will get trickier
상황은 점점 더 까다로워질 것이다
It's right to stay away now
지금은 멀리하는 게 맞다
Stay away?
멀리 있어?
Although I can understand
이해할 수는 있지만
But I feel like Hong Shi will be sad.
그런데 홍시가 서운할 것 같다.
Probably
아마도
I feel like a beating with a cane is inevitable.
지팡이로 때리는 건 어쩔 수 없는 일인 것 같아요.
According to his fiery temper
그의 불같은 성격에 따라
Lynching is also reasonable
린칭도 합리적이다
It seems... at least I will have to lose my arms and legs.
아무래도... 적어도 팔과 다리는 잃어야 할 것 같습니다.
It feels like adults' mood is different from before
어른들의 기분이 예전과는 다른 것 같아요
You were still the same person on your wedding day
당신은 결혼식 날에도 여전히 같은 사람이었습니다
Are they chasing the sedan chair Hong Shi is riding in?
홍시가 타고 있는 가마를 쫓고 있는 걸까요?
Did I...do this?
내가...이랬어?
Did you forget so quickly?
너무 빨리 잊었나요?
rainy day
비오는 날
Are you worried that Hong Shi's sedan chair will fall over?
홍시의 가마가 넘어질까 걱정되시나요?
He also specially asked people to wait on every street where the sedan chair passed.
그는 또한 세단 의자가 지나가는 모든 거리에서 사람들에게 특별히 기다려달라고 요청했습니다.
They are all covered with a lot of dry sand, straw bales, and gravel.
그들은 모두 마른 모래, 짚단, 자갈로 덮여 있습니다.
Isn't it?
그렇지 않나요?
What's the difference between this and chasing the sedan in person?
이게 세단을 직접 쫓는 것과 무슨 차이가 있나요?
Are you still afraid that she will be upset because she got her embroidered shoes wet?
아직도 그녀가 수놓은 신발이 젖었다고 해서 그녀가 화를 낼까 봐 두렵나요?
Obviously he pities her so much
분명히 그 사람은 그녀를 너무 불쌍히 여기고 있어
Why on earth did your master do this?
선생님은 대체 왜 그랬어요?
Are you still worried about whether her sedan chair is shaking?
아직도 그녀의 세단 의자가 흔들리는지 걱정하시나요?
Will it fall?
떨어질까요?
I really can't stand it
정말 못 참겠어
So what should I do?
그러면 어떻게 해야 합니까?
Are you going to find Hong Shi?
홍시를 찾으러 가시나요?
jujube
대추
Go to Sipu Temple and fetch a horse.
사푸사(Sipu Temple)에 가서 말을 가져오세요.
From here, go in by yourself
여기서부터는 혼자서 들어가세요
I was very curious on the way here
여기 오는 길도 너무 궁금했어요
Why is my grandson so angry?
내 손자는 왜 그렇게 화가 났나요?
What? I really don’t want to talk about it again.
무엇? 나는 그것에 대해 다시 이야기하고 싶지 않습니다.
But others saw it
그런데 다른 사람들이 그걸 보니까
I thought you were my husband in this body
이 몸에서는 당신이 내 남편인줄 알았는데
Did you forget so quickly?
너무 빨리 잊었나요?
I am disciplining my family. In my opinion
나는 가족을 징계하고 있습니다. 내 생각에는
This is like an excuse
이건 핑계같아
The way you look at me
당신이 나를 보는 방식
Shaking very violently
아주 격렬하게 흔드는 중
what do you want
당신은 무엇을 원합니까?
I want you not to do anything
아무것도 하지 않았으면 좋겠어
This is a warning
이것은 경고입니다
Experience adults
어른들을 경험해보세요
I have ordered the prisoner to look for you
나는 죄수에게 당신을 찾으라고 명령했습니다
you go
너는 가
It seems your father is looking for you in a hurry
아버지가 급히 너를 찾으시는 것 같구나
Look how anxious this guy's eyes are looking at this body
이 남자가 이 몸을 바라보는 눈빛이 얼마나 불안한지 보세요
It turns out that he has always had this intention in his heart
알고 보니 그 사람은 늘 이런 생각을 마음 속에 품고 있었던 것 같아요.
Anyway
어쨌든
He dares to touch a hair on this body and try it
그는 감히 이 몸의 털 하나라도 만져보고 해본다.
Enzu
엔즈
Your young master waited for you for a long time before leaving
당신의 젊은 주인은 떠나기 전에 오랫동안 당신을 기다렸습니다
Really?
정말요?
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
They seem to be Yijinfu soldiers
이진푸 병사들인 것 같습니다
What are you still doing? Give way
아직도 뭐하고 있어요? 양보하다
Goodbye again, Your Majesty
다시 한번 안녕하십니까, 폐하
Now that everyone is here, at least wait for one meal.
이제 모두 모였으니 최소한 한 끼 정도는 기다려 보세요.
I can't even sit still for this little time
이 짧은 시간 동안 가만히 앉아 있을 수도 없어
So tired, so sleepy
너무 피곤해, 너무 졸려
Who is coming?
누가 오나요?
Are you Ji Tong?
Ji Tong입니까?
Suspected murderer Ji Dong will be released today
살인 용의자 지동, 오늘 석방된다
Arrest Your Majesty
폐하를 체포하세요
What's going on
무슨 일이야?
Changed back
다시 변경됨
Finally changed back...
Finally changed back...
So now Hong Enzu...
그럼 이제 홍엔즈는...
who are you
당신은 누구입니까?
jujube sword
대추 검
Sir
선생님
(Want to hug you Loving you)
(안아주고 싶어 사랑하고 있어)
(I don’t want to let go for a moment)
(한시도 놓치고 싶지 않아)
(Looking as dreamy as ever)
(그 어느 때보다 몽환적인 모습)
(Even if time passes, will you stay with me?)
(시간이 지나도 내 곁에 있어줄래?)
(Come to me now Loving you)
(이제 내게로 와라 사랑해)
The royal family actually sided with the thieves
왕실은 실제로 도둑의 편에 섰습니다.
This has never happened since ancient times
이런 일은 고대 이후로 한번도 없었다
I see your expression as if you want to rush and surrender.
서두르고 항복하고 싶은 표정이 보입니다.
When we first met, I should have taken off my mask to confirm my appearance.
처음 만났을 때 모습을 확인하기 위해 마스크를 벗었어야 했는데.
This way we can avoid these incidents
이렇게 하면 이러한 사고를 피할 수 있습니다
I can also protect you from the beginning.
나도 처음부터 당신을 보호할 수 있어요.
Why are your ideas so extreme?
당신의 생각은 왜 그렇게 극단적입니까?
I'm just worried
걱정이 될 뿐이야
Don't make me think about this damn home
이 빌어먹을 집에 대해 생각하게 만들지 마
generate feelings
감정을 일으키다
Hong Eun-jo is a married woman
홍은조는 유부녀다.
It seems to me that you haven't figured out the situation yet
아직 상황을 파악하지 못한 것 같군요.
That's why I have to put things right
그렇기 때문에 상황을 바로잡아야 해요